there is absolutely no evidence to
support that testosterone levels on
therapy should remain within the ranges
for endogenous production that the most
consistent benefits with testosterone
have actually been with levels that
exceed at the normal range I still get a
lot of comments on this point men um
maybe not in the United States but
internationally in Europe uh we can't
get the compounded testosterone cream
can't I just use andrel on my scrotum
for example no you don't want to use any
alcohol-based product on your scrotum
and that leads me into another talk a
lot of guys like to get into the newest
latest greatest the most fancy that you
know the pharmaceutical industry can uh
give us Atrius the Atrius base it can
work great we've all used it get great
levels with Atrius all right but I had
four or five men that got a
significant you know uh irritation from
a tri that that a Rous was not designed
to apply to your scrotum by the way yeah
you can do it and if you're not one of
those guys that has an issue with it
then fine then it works for you and so
guys that want to use it sure I'll let
you use the Atrius Bas of course but be
warned and uh so just be careful
because you can get good levels but you
can really get great levels with the
other bases as well and you don't run
that risk of uh of that significant
irritation and listen that that it
wasn't a good good issue for them you
know you can't predict when that's going
to happen but but they wanted to use it
they used it and that's what happened so
I've never had that happen with any of
the other bases just a trious base so we
don't want to use an alcohol base and be
warned of the Atrius Bas if you can
tolerate it great you'll probably get
wonderful great levels but you know if
you're one of those guys that that that
base doesn't work so well with then you
you can get some significant irritation
not be happy with it many men also have
other concerns um starting on trt
especially for high hematocrit and
prostate cancer is there something
different between creams and injections
on that point there's there's not
Stephen and I hope that you and I can do
another video in the very near future on
on uh on that's two of the testosterone
mths the prostate cancer and of course
the hematocrit and I'm going to send you
something we finished today that I wrote
on the hematocrit and the secondary ryos
we should do a show just on the
secondary ryos from testosterone and uh
I just watched a video today and you
know uh Dr Thomas OK Conor did a video
on this very topic and he used
literature that is not really literature
it's trash literature and so still a lot
of fearmongering out there about
secondary rosis and I'll forward you
that video as well to YouTube video and
uh and I'll send you what's not really
correct about that video and we can do
another one on that uh the the the
prostate cancer I think that's a
fascinating history behind that and I'd
love to tell the story of the you know
the Morgan Toler and the andreen
saturation model that's a great story
about how it came about that we learned
that testosterone doesn't cause it or
worsen it but instead is protective
against it so I'd love to do a video
with you on that to educate your
listeners I like to go back and look at
the history of of why we've done things
and you know where where that where that
came from a lot of times when it comes
to testost and the these other hormones
you'll find that the way we've been
taught to do things was not actually
based on any medical literature or data
it was just an opinion of someone and it
just kept being propagated not based on
any medical data but the Androgen um
hypothesis on the prostate that that is
fascinating because it's you know it's
a it's well you know it's just going to
be a great it'll be a great topic for a
video without getting into too much
detail detail on it but but it's a
paradox and what confuses people is the
Paradox they know that when men get
prostate cancer they they cut off their
testosterone levels and the prostate
cancer
shrinks but we also know that we give
men testosterone levels even
superphysiological levels it has no
effect on the
or prostate growth well how can that be
that's a paradox yeah so I can explain
that Paradox and we'll explain that
Paradox in a video because I think it's
fascinating very confusing but once you
understand what's going on then then
that then you then it's a it's a great a
it's a great Paradox to understand all
right welcome let's do that in a future
video very soon yeah so then we so the
next thing that we run into all the time
and I know you do too is what's happened
recently is that the word super
physiologic been absolutely
hijacked to mean harm and misuse and
abuse or nothing could be further from
the truth nothing could be further the
truth so let's talk about testosterone
therapy and kind of what's going on with
the guidelines and and the term super
physiologic so Stephen most of the
guidelines including the INR Society
guideline recommend that we raise levels
to the mid-normal physiologic range
which is around 600 normal physiologic
range right now that's that Lab Core
that's accepted is 264 to 916 nanograms
per deciliter now the American Urology
Association recommends that clinicians
use the minimal dosing necessary to
drive testosterone levels to the normal
physiologic range of 450 to 600 we keep
using this word physiologic meaning that
the range that we would naturally
produce now the problem Ste is Stephen
that I don't see many men improving to
any significant degree when we aim for
the mid-normal range
now we've talked about this before but I
can literally show you dozens of studies
where men were given testosterone and it
did not work it did not have a
significant impact on their symptoms and
the common denominator in all of these
studies is that they only raised
testosterone levels a little bit it's
very important to point out that there
is no medical data that supports
treating to a specific number such as
the mid normal physiologic range it's an
opinion it was not based and is not
based on any medical data showing that
if we treat to a level of 450 to 600
that it works better than treating to a
higher number none at all and more
importantly there is absolutely no
evidence to support that testosterone
levels on therapy should remain within
the ranges for endogenous production
once again that recommendation is purely
based on an opinion not on medical data
showing that that works best or doesn't
work best okay we've been doing this for
decades because that's just the way we
were told to do it and we've really
never questioned
why so you know so what I have found as
have you and has many others our good
colleague Dr Neil R rier and many others
is that the most consistent benefits
with testosterone have actually been
with levels that exceeded the normal
range and that the higher levels of
testosterone have correlated with a
greater clinical effect we know that
Stephen we have studies we see it in the
Bas and dose response studies where men
were given 25 50 125 300 600 milligrams
for 20 weeks and those levels were
outside of the normal range and resulted
in greater Improvement in mood cognition
libido and sexual function as well as a
greater increase in lean muscle mass and
decrease in fat
Mass so we still have to ask ourselves
is should we give men what we call a
physiologic dose of testosterone meaning
a dose to keep them in that normal
physiologic range
or should we be using a pharmacologic
dose like we use insulin for for a
physiologic effect should we be
adjusting dosage to treat symptoms or
should we be aiming at a specific number
even though there's no medical data to
support aiming for that specific number
in the mid physiologic
range I've said this over and over again
inadequate doses are ineffective and
that if you only give a little bit of
testosterone it either won't work or it
work just a little bit so we have to
think about this from a clinical
standpoint could it possibly be Stephen
that we are more sensitive and
responsive to our own production based
on the complexity of the physiologic
events involved in stoto Genesis in
other words if you and I could make our
own levels naturally of 800 900 a th000
I think you and I would feel pretty good
as would most men yeah okay the problem
is is when we give
testosterone the end result we're
bypassing all the complex physiologic
events involved in steroidal Genesis and
there's a lot of intermediate enzyme I
mean intermediate hormones involved that
certainly play a role in testosterone's
actions so from a clinical standpoint we
see that we need a level outside of the
normal range in most instances to get
the same physiologic effect we would get
if we produced it ourselves I hope that
that makes sense yeah so when we make it
endogenously we probably would do fine
with a level of 900 but when we get it
exogenously it takes more than what we
can produce physiologically to get the
same results we see this over and over
again clinically and in clinical studies
makes sense yeah so I just think that
when we make it ourselves we're just
more responsive to it and sensitive to
it than when we get the end result which
is just testosterone yeah so we also
know that the normal range for
testosterone has dropped significantly
over the past several decades just in
July of 17 it was 1197 after July 7 2017
it was it was 916 so now what was normal
in June of 2017 is super physiologic so
for instance and then people we we can't
make this up so if a man was seeing as
physician getting testosterone therapy
in 2016 or in June of 2017 and his level
was 1190 it was completely normal
nothing red flag the doctor would Pat
him on the back hey you look great Bill
everything's fine but then he goes back
to that same doctor two months later
after July 2017 he comes back with 1190
again now that doctor is going to lower
his dose because now it's harmful Bill
your level is 1190 and 99116 is the
upper in normal we need to lower your
dose because something bad is going to
happen you're have a heart attack stroke
or blood clot it it you you can't make
this up but it's what's happening is
what is happening so there's been this
this attack on super physiologic when we
see from a clinical standpoint super
physiologic is what it takes in most men
all right and say every man now this is
all going to be misinterpreted as you
know is me saying that well he's just
saying that you just keep raising your
levels you know and just keep going up
up and up more is better I'm not saying
that I'm saying a couple of things here
I'm going to explain in a little more
detail I'm saying that men if we follow
our guidelines do not get enough in most
senses I am saying that number two I am
saying that it typically takes a number
outside of the normal physiologic range
in order to exert a good clinical
response we need to have to Define what
is that so before I do that let me
explain a little more detail now when it
comes to the feel-good effects or
symptomatic improvement with
testosterone there is a plateau there's
a plateau to the Feelgood effects for
raising testosterone levels any further
will have no further effect on
symptomatic Improvement so these men
that say I feel good I feel great dog if
I just increase my dose I might feel
greater no that's not going to occur now
in order to understand the plateau men
need to understand two saturation points
the saturation point of the andin
receptor and enzyme
saturation now in order for testosterone
and its active metabolites to exert
their effects they must first bind to
their receptors and there is a limited
number of receptors available for
binding and once they're fully saturated
then raising levels of testosterone and
its active metabolites any further will
have no further effect and it'll just be
excess so we can continue to raise DHT
in estral for instance to a certain
point and we can measure it in the serum
but it doesn't have any clinical effect
because the receptors are fully
saturated now you know and I know and
all your doctors that you work with know
that more than half the Feelgood effects
from testosterone come from its active
metabolite such as
estradiol now when we increase levels of
testosterone there's going to be a
saturation point of the aromatase enzyme
and the five Alpha reductase enzyme once
you reach the saturation point which is
referred to the V-Max and M Kelis Mitten
kinetics no matter how much you raise
testosterone you cannot raise estradi or
DHT any further so this fear of estradi
continually increasing with increasing
testosterone dosage is not
physiologically possible there is an
enzyme saturation point so ultimately a
plateau we can raise testosterone levels
into the tens of thousands Dallas car
the bodybuilder that that died several
years ago he had a level of over 50,000
nanograms per Des of testosterone but
his estradi was no higher than it would
have been with a testosterone level of
just say, 1500 or 2,000 because he had
reached the saturation Point
testosterone goes up DHT and estrad
plateau and they can't go up any
further so this is what confuses man
it's the misinformation that comes from
the bodybuilding world and why they do
what they do men first of all once again
forget that testosterone Works through
its active metabolites it doesn't work
just as
testosterone okay it works it has a
direct path where it does work just as
testosterone that's on muscle tissue but
all your other tissues your brain your
bones your heart your blood vessels your
sexual organs it has to be converted
into its active metabolites and and the
diversification pathway is when it's
converted into estradiol it diversifies
testosterone's actions and the
amplification pathway is where it's
converted into DHT all right yeah so
bodybuilders use aromatase Inhibitors
and things like that to increase free
testosterone levels because the way test
estone acts on skeletal muscle is
different than the way these active
metabolites act in the brain for
instance so it acts directly on muscle
tissue and with increasing levels of
androgens the and receptor is
upregulated so there's no saturation
point that we have found yet and it
doesn't require an enzyme to act
directly it just acts as testosterone so
there's no enzyme
saturation so you can continue to
increase lean muscle mass
strength with increasing levels of
testosterone another andrens even though
they will have no further effect on
symptomatic Improvement that's an
important point to point out bodybuilder
of level of 10 or 20,000 feels no better
than you or I do maybe worse all right
so the real question to get back to your
original question to Circle back then
what is that saturation point from a
clinical
standpoint that's going to depend on who
you ask Stephen if you were ask somebody
like Peter AA who did a video on
testosterone or several of them recently
he will say that when my patients get a
level of
700 then if they're not feeling any
better not doing any better then I'll
disc continue
testosterone I would fully disagree yeah
sure me too so once again if you were to
ask me where do I see the majority of
men significantly improved clinically
it's the free testosterone around 30 to
60 nanograms per deciliter so those are
the levels where I see the greatest
Improvement and symptoms and every
parameter of Health that I can measure
improves so this typically correlates
with a total testosterone level of
course between 1 and 2,000 we said this
before now some men are find levels less
than that some men may require a little
bit more depending on that free
testosterone level uh and so if I have a
man that I'm treating and his
testosterone level is what we consider
often free testosterone level 50 or
60 any symptoms that are left over at
that time once he's given that time to
work I would not associate with
testosterone
so my saturation point is going to be
you know upwards a 50 or 60 once we
start getting in That 70s 80s well we we
we're past that saturation point and if
you're not feeling any better we need to
look at other causes or go down look at
look down other avenues all right so so
that's what I see from a clinical
standpoint and others have have done the
same thing we look at some work done by
Rebecca Glasser in females now this is
females now all right I mean she
inserted pellets to these women and gave
them symptom questionnaires to determine
whenever their symptoms of and
deficiency uh would would develop and
man what she found out is that these
women when their symptoms resolved had
levels of three or 400 which is four to
six times the upper end of the normal
range for female and whenever the
pellets were dissolving and they started
having their symptoms return their
levels were around 170 or so which is
two to three times the normal range for
women yeah so even in women treating
them with exogenous testosterone
it takes a number typically outside the
normal range to exert a good clinical
effect okay so we should be aiming for
symptomatic Improvement that's a
boogeyman that does not exist Stephen
whenever every parameter if you and I've
talked about this before people will say
well gosh they don't they don't what
harm is they're going to be doing long
term are these men's testosterone being
outside the normal range 1200 whatever
yeah well when every parameter of help
that we can measure improves hemoglobin
A1c inflammatory pyocin go down visceral
fat goes down waste circumference goes
down lipids improve when every parameter
of Health that we can measure improves
at those
levels what is the long-term harm of
that exactly don't see all those
parameters improving with a level of 600
so it appears to me that a too low of a
dose is going to cause more harm than an
optimal dose of course sure so that's
take on what we should be talking about
now is the understanding that the enzyme
saturation andine receptor saturation
understand that there is a plateau to
the Feelgood effects of testosterone
once you get those levels and you have a
consistent level of free testosterone
men need to stop men need to they could
be their Own Worst Enemy you know my my
goal and I tell my patients this is my
job I'm going to optimize your home and
get them as optimal as you can get them
and we're going to be to the point where
you can you can you're have to agree
with me that they can't really be any
better or we could raise a number but
they really can't be any more optimal
and then you just need to check that box
you need to check the hormone box and
now you need to spend all your rest of
your time not on forums or not you know
uh looking to tweak this protocol or
that protocol but instead you check the
hormone box and then you focus on
nutrition you focus on exercise you
focus on your family you focus on you
know your wife your kids your your
friends your hobbies I'm supposed to do
my job to free you up so that you can go
live your life without worrying about
this every day or or ruminating on on
hormones and men cannot use hormones
like they use a stereo equalizer you're
going to have good days bad days good
weeks bad weeks it's just part of life
life is not fun all the time life is not
easy all the time and you can't address
those hard times or stressful situations
by thinking you're going to tweak your
hormones to get you through it uh every
year every year I'll get two or three
men that'll call me up do doesn't work
anymore I feel worse than I did before I
started now I used have a conversation
with them first but now I'll go ahead
and get their Labs that's what they want
I got to get my labs see what's wrong
because it's just not working anymore
okay so I get their labs they come back
and Stephen there's not been one
instance that this has not been the case
not one so their Labs come back we meet
well bill I got your levels back well
your levels are the same in fact Bill
they're better they're either the same
or always better than they were when
they felt their greatest I said bill
that your levels are Iden iCal or in
fact they're better than they were last
time we talked and you felt great and
everything was
wonderful understand hormones don't stop
working Stephen people do but hormones
don't all right they don't just all of a
sudden lose their effectivess they don't
that's not how they work at all okay
there's no receptor you know burnout
anything like that that's just rubbish
but so then I'll said well bill now that
we established that it's not hormones
tell me what else is going on and these
are the answers that I've gotten from
all these number one doc my wife had an
affair doc I'm getting a divorce doc I
lost my job doc I'm working two jobs I'm
working my self ragged you know doc our
child was on drugs and now in rehab and
Doc my mother-in-law moved in who has
Alzheimer's and it's just been terribly
stressful so comment an automator is
always stress stress is the great
equalizer I don't care how great your
hormones are if you're under periods of
stress you're not going to feel as good
when you're as when you're not obviously
and the men that have the hardest time
with this the ones that are typically
the hardest to treat are the guys that
are in their early 30s life becomes real
at that age group I mean they just
becomes real you're not really young
anywhere because you're not in your 20s
but you're definitely not anywhere near
old but you're kind of caught up in that
where you've usually got a wife maybe
young children got a a house payment a
car payment you're establishing a career
that is stressful yeah you know it can
it can you're not going to feel your
greatest all the time and you can't use
hormones to overcome it right so just
the key is that there are so many
factors that go how we feel and function
every day besides hormones but once you
get your hormones fully
optimal then you should just check that
box and move on to every other aspect of
your life that you can improve on
exactly take home message Stephen I'll
get off the soap box
now awesome um so I I guess um the whole
message is um that we should try to
raise or total testosterone to a certain
number whatever that is it might be
superphysiological of course to have a
free tea between 30 and 60 that's
correct for most men some less some a
little bit more but but that's where and
then you have to give it time to work
this doesn't work in days or weeks this
is months and then it builds on itself
year after year yeah the greatest
Improvement that I see when a man for
starts it is give them six to 12 months
for sure and make sure they have optimal
levels and then it works Improvement
will occur year to year as long as the
man puts in what I call The Sweat Equity
you and I have the easy job we can
provide them with hormones and get their
levels optimal they have the difficult
job they have to eat right they have to
exercise they have to try to get enough
sleep and reduce their stress so they
have the hard job and testosterone won't
make any that easy testostrone will
reward effort that's what it does if you
if you put in the work you'll be
rewarded for that work it rewards effort
but it won't do it by itself I think
that you've done a good job with
everyone that you've had on your podcast
Dave Le's come around really done s
putting out some good content uh you
know recently and because he's you know
I'm so proud to see that he's telling it
like it is and and I'm glad to hear that
because that's just the way it should
[Music]
be